Okay, okay, we get a sound check, can everybody hear me?
好的，我们检查一下声音，大家都能听到我说话吗？
Yep.
是的。
Okay, good, whatever, let's going.
好的，我们开始。
Good afternoon, or good evening or good morning or good night, wherever you are.
下午好，傍晚好，早上好，晚上好，无论你在哪里。
Today's lecture, I'm going to be, about page fault.
今天的讲座，我要讲的是页面错误。
In particular, we're gonna plan is to,
具体来说，我们的计划的是，
cover implement, implemented number of virtual memory features, using page faults.
使用页面错误，实现几个虚拟内存功能。使用页面错误。
And the features that we're gonna be looking at are lazy allocation,
我们接下来要看的功能是懒分配，
which is the topic of the next lab.
这是下一个实验的主题。
Yeah, we're gonna look at demand, copy-and-write fork, demand paging, and memory map files, mmap.
是的，我们还要看，写入时复制 fork ，按需调页，以及内存映射文件， mmap 。
And, um.
还有，嗯。
And almost you know in sort of [] operating system actually implements all these features,
几乎所有操作系统都实现了这些功能，
look inside of Linux, you'll see all these features actually are implemented.
深入 Linux ，你会看到所有这些功能都已经实现。
In xv6, as it stands none of them are implemented.
在 xv6 中，目前（这些功能）一个都没有实现。
In fact, what page fault does in xv6,
实际上，页面错误在 xv6 中做的是，
if page fault happens in user space, basically kill the process, whatever [interesting].
如果在用户空间中发生页面错误，就杀死这个进程，没有别的[事情]。
And so in this lecture, we're going to explore
所以在这次演讲中，我们要探索一下，
what interesting things, you could do in the page fault handler to actually implement these features.
可以在页面错误处理器中做什么有趣的事情，来实现这些功能。
So this lecture a little bit less walking through code and understanding existing code, a little bit more design level.
所以这节课，减少了演示代码，更多是设计层面的。
In the sense, we don't even have code to look at.
从这个意义上来说，我们甚至没有代码可看。
Another thing that's important to mention is lazy allocation,
另一个重要的东西是懒分配，
is topic of the next lab,
是下一个实验的主题，
hopefully it will push out today.
希望它能在今天推出。
And copy-on-write fork, it's gonna be a topic of one of the labs
写入时复制 fork ，也是一个实验的主题，
and mmap is going to be another topic of one of the subsequent labs.
还有， mmap 也是后续实验的另一个主题。
So this is gonna be one of the interesting parts of an operating system,
所以这是操作系统中最有趣的部分之一，
we're gonna be spending quite a bit of time on these labs.
我们将在这些实验上花费很多时间。
Now, you know before diving into details,
现在，在深入讨论细节之前，
it is probably helpful to take a little bit of step back
回顾一下可能会有帮助，
and so you can think about virtual memory having two major benefits.
你可以认为虚拟内存主要有两个好处。
One is isolation, so isolation in the sense that,
一个是隔离，从某种意义上说，隔离是，
virtual memory allows the operating system to give every application it's own address space,
虚拟内存允许操作系统，给每个应用程序提供自己的地址空间，
and so it's impossible for one application to, or by accidental or maliciously to modify another application address space.
使一个应用程序不可能意外地或恶意地修改另一应用程序的地址空间。
It also provides isolation between user and kernel address space as we talk about quite a bit
它还提供了用户和内核地址空间之间的隔离，我们讨论过的，
and as you've seen in the page table lab.
也是你们在页表实验中看到的那样。
But sort of another view or another benefit of virtual memory,
虚拟内存的另一个好处，
you know alluded to a couple times earlier
之前我提到过几次，
is that it provides a level of indirection,
它提供了一定程度的间接性。
you know, the processor instructions, you know only use virtual addresses,
处理器指令，只使用虚拟地址，
but the kernel gets to sort of define the mapping from virtual addresses to physical addresses,
而内核定义了从虚拟地址到物理地址的映射，
and that allows all kinds of interesting -, interesting features,
它允许各种有趣的功能，
like the ones we're gonna be talking about in this lecture.
就像我们要在这节课中讨论的那样。
The. Second.
这个，稍等。
And the.
还有。
The kernel controls this particular mapping from virtual to physical address space
内核控制着从虚拟地址空间到物理地址空间的映射，
and most so far in xv6, that mapping has to be quite boring,
到目前为止，xv6 的映射都很无趣，
in fact the kernel is mostly direct mapping
事实上，内核主要是恒等映射，
and a couple of interesting things that we do, xv6 does,
xv6 做了几件有趣的事情，
which is mapping one as we've seen, the trampoline page,
其中一个我们可以看到的是 trampoline 页。
allowed kernel map one page into many address spaces,
允许内核将一个页面映射到多个地址空间，
another interesting case that we've seen is the guard page,
另一个可以看到的有趣的例子是守护页，
to protect stack, both in the kernel, in kernel space and user space and kernel space.
它用来在用户空间和内核空间中保护栈。
But if you think about it,
但是你想一下，
so far that mapping has been relatively static,
目前为止，这种映射是相对静态的，
you know we set it up once, you know maybe per user, kernel page table mapping,
我们设置一次，用户或内核页表映射，
setup once in the beginning and processes once at fork
在开始时设置一次，还有进程 fork 时设置一次，
and they're sort of the kernel doesn't really do anything else with this mapping.
然后内核不会对这个映射做任何其他的事情。
And what page fault gives us is actually to make these maps dynamic.
而页面错误给我们的是，让这些映射变为动态的。
So using page faults, and we can change,
所以使用页面错误，我们可以改变，
the kernel can change the mapping, sort of dynamically on the fly.
内核可以动态地改变映射。
And this turns out to be extremely powerful mechanism,
这是一种非常强大的机制，
so you can combine page tables and page faults,
将页表和页面错误结合起来，
you, have enormous, kernel has an enormous amount of flexibility.
内核有了极大的灵活性。
And the flexibility [comes down], because you can change the level of [direction] on the fly.
灵活性是因为你可以在运行时修改指向。
And, so what we're going to be doing is basically
所以我们要做的是，
looking at all kinds of usages of this dynamic re-mapping or dynamic changing of the page tables,
研究这种动态映射或动态修改页表的各种用法，
that gives you interesting features.
这给你带来有趣的功能。
So the first thing, we may want to think about,
所以我们要考虑的第一件事，
is a little bit, is what information is needed,
是需要什么信息，
you know if here in a page fault happens,
如果发生页面错误，
and, kernel wants to respond to this page fault,
内核需要响应这个页面错误，
you know what information does it need to actually be able to respond.
那么它需要什么信息才能做出回应。
You know sort of quite you know obviously, we'd like to have the virtual address of, virtual address of faulting,
很明显，我们需要错误的虚拟地址，
where gonna cause page fault.
（这个地址）会引起页面错误。
Say you want to see this, the faulting virtual address.
比如，你想看到这个，错误虚拟地址。
And you've seen presumably some of these panic calls in your page fault lab,
你可能已经在页表实验中，看到了一些这样的错误，
and you know the kernel actually has extra [status],
内核实际上有额外的状态，
in fact that prints them out when we actually page fault happens
当我们发生页面错误时，把它们打印出来，
and it happens to be sitting in the stval register.
它在 stval 寄存器里。
So when user application, causes a page fault,
所以，当用户应用程序导致页面错误时，
the page fault basically invokes the same trap machinery,
页面错误调用相同的陷阱机制，
that Robert discussed in the last lecture,
像 Robert 在上一节课中谈到的，
it's almost completely identical,
它们几乎完全相同，
but in the case of page fault, it also will put the faulting address into that stval register.
但是在页面错误的情况下，它还会把错误地址放入 stval 寄存器中。
So that is, one thing that we probably want to know,
这就是，我们可能要知道的一件事，
the second thing that we probably want to know is the type of fault.
我们可能想知道的第二件事，是错误类型。
Because it may be, in terms of,
因为可能，
we may want to do respond different differently
我们可能希望做出不同的回应，
in terms of to page fault due to a load instruction
对于加载指令引起的页面错误，
or page fault due to a store instruction,
或由于保存指令的页面错误，
or page fault due to a jump instruction.
或由于跳转指令引起的页面错误。
And, so in fact if you look at the RISC-V documentation.
如果你查看 RISC-V 文档。
Here's the RISC-V documentation in here,
这里是 RISC-V 文档，
in the scause, we that we was mentioning the trap lecture,
在 scause 中，我们在 trap 课程中提到的，
there are, a member of causes that actually related to page faults,
有一些与页面错误有关的原因，
so yeah but if you look at number thirteen, it's a load page fault,
是的，看一下编号 13 ，是一个加载页面错误，
number fifteen is a store page fault,
编号 15 是一个存储页面错误，
and number twelve is an instruction page fault.
而编号 12 是指令页面错误。
So these are, in the scause register, then we get that information.
所以，这些在 scause 寄存器中，然后我们就能得到这些信息。
And so there's three different types, you know read write and instruction.
所以，有三种不同的类型，读，写和指令。
And just go back,
往回走一点，
you know the one scause, you know actually was caused by the [ecall] instruction,
有一个 scause 实际上是由 ecall 指令引起的，
to actually the kernel transfer is number eight.
内核传输是编号 8 。
Alright, so that's the one that we saw in the trap lecture,
好的，这就是我们在 trap 讲座中看到的，
that we spend a lot of time thinking about in that trap lecture.
我们在 trap 演讲中花了很多时间思考。
But basically all the other page faults or exceptions
但基本上所有其他页面错误或异常，
use the same mechanism to transfer from user space to kernel space
使用相同的机制从用户空间到内核空间，
and once in kernel space, in the case of the page fault,
一旦进入内核空间，出现页面错误，
the stval register set, scause register set.
就设置 stval 寄存器，设置 scause 寄存器。
Then the third thing, that we probably want to know is
然后，我们可能想知道的第三件事是，
the instruction or address the virtual address of instruction, that cause the page fault.
引起页面错误的指令的虚拟地址。
And, you know, anybody remember
还有，有没有人还记得，
where you know from the trap lecture, where the where the instruction is, where the addresses?
从 trap 课程中，指令在哪里，地址在哪里？
Anybody?
有人知道吗？
Is it sepc? Yeah exactly.
是 sepc 吗？是的，正确。
And there's this register, sepc correct, the supervisor exception exception program counter,
这里有个 sepc 寄存器，管理者模式异常程序计数器，
there is where it is and where is that saved as part of the trap handling code?
作为陷阱处理代码的一部分，它保存在哪里？
In the trapframe?
在 trapframe ？
Yeah, there's in the trapframe correct,
是的，在 trapframe 中，
there's trapframe epc, actually has the exception program counter.
这里有一个 trapframe epc ，包含异常程序计数器。
So we think about the hardware mechanism actually what xv6 does,
所以，我们考虑一下 xv6 所做的硬件机制，
we have three pieces of information are probably extremely valuable to us, when we get actually page fault,
当出现页面错误时，有三条可能对我们非常有价值的信息，
namely the address of cause fault, the type of fault
即引起错误的地址，错误类型，
and the exception program counter like where did it happen to user space.
还有异常程序计数器，比如它发生在用户空间的什么地方。
And the reason we care a lot about the exception program counter is
我们关心异常程序计数器的原因是，
because when we probably want to repair, in the handler going to repair the pagetable
因为当我们想在处理程序中修复页表时，
and then we're gonna basically restart the same instruction
然后我们会重新运行相同的指令，
and hopefully the after repairing the page fault or reparing the pagetables
希望在修复页面错误或修复页表之后，
that instruction can just run without any trouble.
那条指令可以继续运行。
And so it's important that we can be resume the instruction that actually that we cause fault.
所以，可以重新执行引起错误的指令是很重要的。
Is that all makes sense?
这些能理解吗？
Okay, so now I'm gonna look at,
好的，现在我要看一下，
you know the basic mechanism and basic information that the RISC-V is actually giving us
实际上 RISC-V 给我们提供的基础机制和基本信息，
and I want to look at, basically go through a list of, you know features
我想看一份功能清单，
that will help us, you know we understand actually
可以帮助我们理解，
how we can use the page fault handler to repair the pagetable and do interesting things.
我们如何使用页面错误程序修复页表，并做一些有趣的事情。
So the first thing I want to look at is allocation, in particular, you know sbrk.
所以我想看的第一件事是分配，特别是， sbrk 。
So sbrk is the system call, that xv6 provides,
所以， sbrk 是 xv6 提供的系统调用，
that allows an application to basically grow grow its heap
它允许应用程序增加自己的堆空间，
when the application starts sbrk points here,
当应用程序启动时， sbrk 指向这里，
at the bottom of the heap, you know top of the stack,
位于堆的底部，栈的顶端，
in fact it's the same place where you know p->sz basically you know points to.
实际上，这也是 p->sz 指向的地方。
And so when sbrk called,
所以，当调用 sbrk 时，
for example, sbrk called, it's like one two three four five,
比如 sbrk 1 2 3 4 5 ，
you know the number of pages that you know you want to allocate,
数字是你想要分配的页数，
the sbrk system call basically bumps up you know this boundary, to something there.
sbrk 系统调用提高这个界限，到这里某个地方。
And that and so what, that means that when the sbrk actually happens or sbrk system call is called,
这就是说，当调用 sbrk 系统调用时，
the kernel allocation physical memory, map it into the address space of the user application,
内核分配物理内存，映射到用户用用程序的地址空间，
zero the memory and then basically return from the system call.
将内存置零，然后从系统调用返回。
And after time and the application can grow, you know that physical memory or memory that it needs
之后，应用程序可以增长它需要的物理内存，
or it might want by just calling multiple times to sbrk.
或者它可能多次调用 sbrk 。
The application also decrease or shrink its address space by calling sbrk with a negative number.
应用程序还可以使用一个负数调用 sbrk ，来缩小它的地址空间。
But I want to focus on the case where we're growing the address space.
但是，我想把重点放在增加地址空间的情况下。
And in xv6 as it is, the sbrk is eager
在 xv6 中， sbrk 是急切的，
or does what we're gonna call eager allocation,
或者我们称之为[急分配]，
namely as soon as the sbrk called,
也就是说，只要一调用 sbrk ，
the kernel will immediately allocate the physical memory that the application is asking for.
内核会立即分配应用程序需要的物理内存。
And it turns out that in practice,
在实践中，
it's actually hard for applications to predict, how much memory they need,
应用程序很难预测，它需要多少内存，
so, typically applications tend to over ask,
所以，通常情况下，应用程序会多申请，
and so they ask a lot more than they really need,
所以，它们申请的比需要的多，
and often that means which means that basically you know the address space will grow quite a bit,
通常，这意味着地址空间会有比较大的增长，
even with memory does actually never used by the application.
即使应用程序从未使用到的内存。
You might think that was stupid, how could that happen,
你可能认为那很愚蠢，怎么会发生这种事，
well, you know, think about if you write an application program
嗯，想想如果你写一个程序，
and the typical application program maybe reach an input
典型的程序可能会输入，
or has a matrix that uses for some computation,
或者具有用于某些计算的矩阵，
and often the application writer sort of plans for the worst case,
通常，应用程序编写者会为最坏的情况做准备，
you know allocates memory for the biggest matrix, the application might never ever need.
为最大的矩阵分配内存，而应用程序可能永远不需要。
But in the common case,
但是一般情况下，
application maybe computes are much smaller input or a much smaller matrix
应用程序的计算，可能是小得多的输入或小得多的矩阵，
and so it's quite common, in fact for application programmers
事实上，对于应用程序程序员来说，这很常见，
and probably if you think about your own applications written
如果你考虑一下自己编写的应用程序，
to actually over ask and actually [own] their use.
过多申请并拥有它们使用（的内存）。
And we'd like to, principle, not a big problem,
我们希望，原则上，不是什么大问题，
but you know using actually virtual memory and page fault handlers,
使用虚拟内存和页面错误处理程序，
we can actually totally totally responded at, in sort of an intelligent manner,
我们完全可以以一种聪明的方式做出回应，
and, by basically doing lazy allocation.
通过使用懒分配。
And the basic idea is very simple,
它的基本想法很简单，
at sbrk, we're basically gonna do almost nothing,
在 sbrk 中我们基本上什么也不做，
the only thing that we need to know, remember of course that we get grow address space,
我们唯一要做的是，记住增加了地址空间，
so the only thing we are going to be doing is actually bumping up you know p->sz, you know, whatever with the number,
所以，我们唯一要做的就是 p->sz 增加一个数，
you know set p->sz to one of the new size plus you know n
把 p->sz 设置成一个加上 n 的大小，
and you know what n is the amount of memory that's allocated.
n 是内存的分配量。
And then you know, that we don't allocate,
然后，我们没有分配，
the kernel doesn't allocate any physical memory at that particular point of time,
内核在这时没有分配任何物理内存，
it doesn't zero, there's absolutely nothing.
它什么也没做。
Then, at some point the application will use or might use that memory, correct,
然后，在某个时刻，应用程序可能会使用该内存，
if it is actually one of the pieces of memory that it really needs
如果那是它需要的一块内存，
and that will cause a page fault.
这会导致页面错误。
Because we didn't map, that memory actually into the page map yet,
因为，我们没有映射那块内存到页面映射中，
and so, if we do reference virtual address, you know above, you know, this p->sz, but below p->sz plus n,
因此，如果我们引用虚拟地址，高于 p->sz 但是低于 p->sz + n ，
what we'd like to be happening is that you know the kernel allocate a page and restarts instruction.
我们希望的是，内核分配一个页面并重新启动指令。
So, if we get a page fault
所以，如果我们遇到页面错误，
and we see that the virtual address is bigger than p->sz, it's below, sorry, these below p->sz, for p->sz,
并且看到虚拟地址高于 p->sz ，抱歉，低于 p->sz ，
then we know that this must be virtual address I guess above stack,
而且这个地址高于栈，
we know that this is an address that actually comes out of the heap,
我们知道这是一个堆中的地址，
but for which we, the kernel hasn't allocated any physical memory yet.
但是，内核还没有为它分配任何物理内存。
And so the response to this page fault could be reasonably straightforward,
对这个页面错误的反应可以很直接，
in the page fault handler itself, we can allocate a page,
在页面错误处理程序中，我们可以分配一个页面，
using kalloc, allocate one page, zero the page, map the page into the pagetable,
使用 kalloc ，分配一页，置零，并映射到页表中，
so updating the pagetables, then basically restart the instruction.
更新页表，然后重启指令。
So, for example is a load instruction or a store instruction
比如，加载指令或保存指令，
that loads from or to read you know from not allocated piece of memory that actually the process has,
从进程已经包含，但实际未分配的内存中加载或读取，
now after we mapped in this physical page, the restart instruction should just work.
现在，我们映射了这个物理页面后，重启命令应该可以正常工作。
Amiar, go ahead.
Amiar ，继续。
Right, so I was wondering in the case where we're doing eager allocation,
好的，我想知道在急分配的情况下，
and there comes a point where process consumes so much memory,
某一时刻，进程消耗很多内存，
that it actually exhausts the physical memory resource,
它耗尽物理内存资源，
if we don't do eager allocation, we do lazy instead,
如果我们不使用急分配，而使用懒分配，
at what point would the application know that there is no physical memory.
在什么情况下，应用程序才会知道没有物理内存。
Yeah, that's a great question,
是的，这是个很好的问题，
you know, basically you know it almost looks through the application,
基本上，从应用程序的角度看，
there's this illusion of unlimited physical amount of memory.
有无限多的内存。
You know, at some point of course, you know you might use so much,
当然在某些时候，你可能用得太多了，
you know that basically use all physical memory,
基本上使用了所有物理内存，
and so if then it touches one more page,
所以，如果它再多申请一页，
which there's no physical memory present at that particular point in time.
这个时候，物理内存不够用了。
Then you know there's a couple of actions that the kernel can take
然后内核可以采取几个操作，
and I'll talk about more sophisticated ones later,
稍后我会谈到更复杂的问题，
what you're gonna be doing in the lazy lab
你要在 lazy 实验中做的是，
is you know if the memories up and there's no more free memory,
如果内存增长到没有空闲内存，
you just return an error, actually kill the process in that particular case.
在这种情况下，你只需要返回一个错误，并杀死进程。
And so because you're out of memory, so there's nothing kernel can do
而且因为内存不足，内核也不能做什么，
and at that point, you know return or kill the process.
这时，只能返回或杀死进程。
That's you're going to do in lazy lab,
这就是你要在 lazy 实验中做的，
we'll see later in this lecture,
我们稍后会在这节课中看到，
you can be more sophisticated than that.
你可以做的比这更复杂。
And I think this is generally brings up a topic
我想这引出了一个话题，
that is we have a collection of processes running on an operating system,
我们有一组运行在操作系统上的进程，
there's a limited amount of physical memory,
而物理内存是有限的，
and that limited physical memory must be shared in some way between the applications.
并且这些有限的物理内存必须以某种方式在应用程序之间共享。
And so I'll talk a little bit much more about it in 10,20 minutes.
我将在 10 20 分钟后，详细讨论这个问题。
Okay, there's a question in the chat.
好的，聊天窗口中有个问题。
Why is the condition virtual address, virtual address [booms] doesn't start at zero.
为什么虚拟地址比较不是从零开始的。
OK, there's a question about this particular check here.
好的，这是一个关于这个检查的问题。
So, remember, we have our stack here,
所以，这里有栈，
and we have our data here and we have our text in user process
这里有进程的数据和文本，
and basically we've bumped up p->sz to something bigger.
我们把 p->sz 增加到更大的位置。
We've bumped up the [growth], we havn't the allocated memory here yet,
我们已经增加了[]，但是没有分配内存，
so this memory has not been physically allocated yet,
所以这个内存还没有物理分配，
so this check this check if the address falls below p->sz
所以这个检查，如果地址落在 p->sz 以下，
and it actually is a valid address in the user address space,
它是用户地址空间中的有效地址，
if there above p->sz, presumably that's a programming error,
如果在 p->sz 之上，可能是编程错误，
and the program or user applications trying to reference in memory that actually doesn't have.
用户应用程序试图在内存中，引用实际上不属于它的内存。
Hopefully that answered the question.
希望我回答了这个问题。
Yeah, thank you.
是的，谢谢。
Okay, so to get a little bit of feel, you know what it actually means and this lazy allocation,
好的，为了感受一下懒分配是什么，
and that's probably, the only sort of programming or code things that were going to be doing today is,
这可能是今天唯一要做的编程或代码，
let's try to sort of sketch out or look actually how will look in the in code.
让我们看看它在代码中的样子。
When the [], you see that it will be surprising easy
当[]，你可以看到它非常简单，
and furthermore it's probably big help for the lazy lab.
另外，这可能对 lazy 实验有很大帮助。
And so, hopefully that will help you get going pretty straightforwardly.
所以，希望这能帮助你更直接地开始。
And at large [resources] to look at a couple page faults.
让我们看几个页面错误。
I have a question, actually we got a point,
我有个问题，我有一个想法，
why do we actually need to kill the application,
为什么我们杀死应用程序，
could the operating system just to return like a [negative], out of memory trying to something else.
操作系统能不能返回一个负数，内存不足什么的。
Let's respond to the question a little bit later,
我们稍后再回答这个问题，
in the page fault, we're going to just kill the process,
在页面错误中，我们直接杀死该进程，
but you know we could be more sophisticated, in [] lab,
但是，我们可以在[]实验中做得更复杂，
real kernels are more sophisticated.
真正的内核更复杂。
Okay, although in the end they might still kill,
好的，虽然最后它们可能还是被杀死，
if there's no more memory, what what's there to be done,
如果没有更多的内存，还有什么能做的，
you know there's basically no choice.
我们基本上别无选择。
Okay, so the first thing we're going to modify,
好的，所以首先我要修改的，
so remember that's growproc you know actually grows to address space with the application,
growproc 增加应用程序的地址空间，
allocates memory and all that kind of stuff,
分配内存和其他的东西，
we're just not gonna do that,
我们不会这么做，
you're just gonna set p->sz, you know to p->sz plus n.
你只需要设置 p->sz 为 p->sz + n 。
So let's assume that number only growing and not worry about shrinking for now,
现在，让我们假设数字只是增长而不用考虑减少，
and that is what we're gonna be doing.
这就是我们要做的。
So this grows the virtual address space by n, that's all we're going to be doing.
所以，这会使虚拟地址空间增加 n ，这就是我们要做的。
Let's see if I can make no programming mistakes,
让我们看看，是否有编程错误，
I did make a programming mistake, I guess.
我想，我有一个编程错误。
I don't have proc p here, so myproc.
我这里没有 proc p ，所以 myproc 。
Yeah, so the program just runs as usual we boot,
是的，所以程序只是像往常启动一样运行，
I think if we do like echo hi, we're gonna get actually a page fault
我想如果我们执行 echo hi ，我们会遇到一个页面错误，
and the reason that we get a page fault is because,
我们出现页面错误的原因是，
the shell who's gonna fork you know echo and then the child's gonna exec echo,
shell 要 fork echo ，然后子进程执行 echo ，
the shell actually allocate some memory,
shell 实际上分配了一些内存，
and so the shell calls sbrk and things are not looking good,
因此 shell 调用 sbrk ，然后事情不太好，
but it's sort of interesting to look at, you know, the information here,
但是，这里的信息看起来比较有趣，
so here's it prints out the scause register, the value scause and it's fifteen.
这里打印出 scause 寄存器，它的值是 15 。
Anybody, remember what fifteen is?
有没有人记得 15 是什么？
You know from that table I just show you a little bit a while ago,
从刚在我展示的那张表中，
actually used to write or store page fault.
用于写入或存储页面错误。
We see this process three, that's probably the shell.
我们看到的进程 3 ，可能是 shell 。
And we actually see the exception program counter, it's one two a four
我们实际上看到的是异常程序计数器，它是 12a4 ，
and we see the address given the virtual address in which we fault, which is 4008.
我们可以看到发生错误的虚拟地址是 4008 。
And so let's look at the, you know, we can look at the assembly of the shell,
那么让我们来看一下 shell 的汇编代码，
makefile nice for us, nice enough for us to actually generate that
makefile 为我们生成了该文件，
and we can look at the address 12a4.
我们可以看看地址 12a4 。
And you know we see indeed, you know, there's a store instruction right,
我们看到是个一个存储指令，
the store instruction and, it looks like that's where we're faulting.
这个存储指令看起来就是发生错误的地方。
So you know scroll back a little bit and look at this assembly here,
往后滚动一点，看这里的汇编代码，
you know we see that actually this is in part of the implementation of malloc.
我们看到这实际上是 malloc 实现的一部分。
So that seems totally reasonable, here's malloc implementation,
所以这看起来是完全合理的，这是 malloc 实现，
not surprising that we, presumably we use sbrk to get some memory for implementing the user malloc.
这并不奇怪，我们使用 sbrk 获得一些内存来实现用户 malloc 。
And, we're basically initializing a free list of the use the memory that we've just gotten from the kernel,
我们把从内核得到内存，初始化为一个空闲列表，
and this line 12a4, [] writes, you know, I guess write something insides
这个 12a4 行，我猜是写入一些东西，
but we were writing to memory that actually hasn't been allocated.
但我们正在写入实际上未分配的内存。
Another reason that we could see that the memory probably not allocated is,
我们可以看到内存可能未分配的另一个原因是，
the I think shell actually has four pages of text and data
我认为 shell 实际上有四页文本和数据，
and we're basically sitting just above the fourth page, in the fifth page,
我们正在第四页的上方，在第五页，
in fact we're sitting eight bytes above it,
实际上，我们的位置比它高出 8 个字节，
that sort of makes sense,
这在某种程度上是有道理的，
look at the instruction again, where at 124a,
再看一下指令，在  ，
you know see here basically probably a0 holds 4000 and eight is the additional offset,
这里 a0 可能放的是 4000 ， 8 是额外的偏移量，
you know that we're actually referencing, that's the fault.
我们实际上引用的，这就是错误所在。
And now what we like to do, is you know do something slightly more sophisticated.
现在我们想做的是，做一些稍微复杂一点的事。
Then, we're gonna be doing and so let's go to trap.c,
然后，我们要做的是，让我们到 trap.c ，
and look at usertrap, this happens in usertrap,
查看 usertrap ，这个发生在 usertrap ，
usertrap is the function that we, Robert had discussed a week ago,
usertrap 是 Robert 上周讨论过的函数，
and it just goes through the different causes and perform some action,
它只是对于不同的原因，执行一些操作，
so we're a little bit, here's, this line is scause eight
所以，这一行是 scause 8 ，
and you know that's the point we're going to process system calls.
就是我们要处理系统调用的点。
Then there's a line that checks whether there was any a device interrupt and processes inside of device interrupt,
然后，有一行用于检查是否有设备中断，并处理设备中断，
and if there's none of those to happen, then basically we get this a trap and the process of being killed.
如果这些都没有发生，我们得到一个 trap ，并杀死进程。
And basically what we need to do is,
我们需要做的是，
you need to add some code here, that you know checks for another case, right,
需要在这里添加一些代码，检查另一种情况，
basically I guess the case that we want to [] a line is if r_scause,
我想我们要做的是，添加一行 if r_scause ，
[] call it like it's r_scause is fifteen,
r_scause 是不是 15 ，
we want to do something else.
我们想做点别的事。
Does that make sense?
这个能理解吗？
So what do you want to do here,
那么，你想在这里做什么，
what is sort of the plan for [] for these couple lines of code?
对这些代码，你的计划什么？
We want to check if p->sz is more than the virtual address that in stval, perhaps.
我们可能要检查 p->sz 是不是大于 stval 中的虚拟地址。
Yeah, go ahead.
是的，继续。
Oh, and this is the case then do something like uvmalloc, I think.
然后，我认为做一些像 uvmalloc 做的事情。
That's one way we could do it,
这是我们可以做的一种方法，
so I'm going to cut some corners just for a demo
因为只是一个演示，我会偷懒一下，
and presumably in the lab itself, you will need to do a little bit more work,
在实验里，你需要多做一点工作，
but basically here's the sort, I think [] code section of code, we need.
但是，这是我们需要的代码片段。
So let's see.
让我们看看。
Where I was.
我在哪里。
Here's usertrap, let me just kind of paste into it.
这是 usertrap ，让我把它粘贴进去。
And we can look at, you know just a print statement for debugging
我们可以看看，只有一条用于调试的 print 语句，
and basically we're going to do in this handler, I'm gonna allocate a physical page.
我们要在这个处理程序里做的是，分配一个物理页。
If there's no physical page, mean we're out of memory, we're gonna kill the process for now,
如果没有物理页面，意味着我们内存不足，我们要杀死这个进程，
if there's a physical page, we'll zero the page,
如果有物理页面，我们将页面清零，
then we just map the page at the appropriate address, in the address space of the user
然后，我们只需要将页面映射到用户地址空间中适当的地址，
in particular map it on the rounded down virtual address,
[特别]将其映射到四舍五入的虚拟地址上，
so the faulting address 4008 here, and so that's eight bytes into the fifth page
所以，这里的错误地址是 4008 ，是第五页中的第八个字节，
and we want to map that physical page at the bottom of the physical, virtual page, so at 4000,
我们想要映射这个物理页面到虚拟页面的底部，所以是 4000 ，
rounded down to 4000 then we map 4000 to this physical page.
四舍五入到 4000 ，然后将 4000 映射到这个物理页面。我们将4000映射到此物理页面。
And then of course we have to set the usual permission bits, you know u bit, read and write.
当然，我们还要设置常用的权限位， u 标志位，还有读和写。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Yeah, I guess I can get rid of this line.
我想我可以删掉这一行。
So let's see, let's try it out.
让我们看看，试一下。
And I guess I made some mistakes.
我想，我犯了一些错误。
I think that on the else, you don't have an opening bracket at the bottom.
我认为在 else 那里，你在底部没有开始的括号。
Oh yeah, yeah, so if, I do I do I need one more, oh yeah.
哦，是的，所以，我需要多一个（括号），哦，是的。
Oh, sorry, I mean on the else right here, you don't have an opening bracket right,
哦，抱歉，我是说在 else 的右边，你没有正确的括号，
like when is else printf usertrap unexpected scause.
else 是 printf usertrap unexpected scause 那里的。
And hopefully all [work], excellent, so echo hi.
希望都是正常的，太棒了，所以 echo hi 。
Now, of course we're going to be optimistic and hope it works,
现在，我们当然很乐观，希望它能工作，
I'll tell you it won't work,
我告诉你这是不能工作的，
but we did get two page faults right,
但我们确实得到了两个页面错误，
we gotta page fault 4008, you know primarily [],
我们得到了页面错误 4008 ，这个是前面看到的，
because we've got another page fault.
[因为]我们又得到了另一个页面错误。
And so the only problem we've left is there's a uvmunmap complaining that,
所以我们剩下的问题是 uvmunmap 报错，
as complaining that there are some page that we're trying to unmap is actually not mapped.
指出一些想要取消映射的页实际上并没有映射。
And what could it be.
那会是什么呢。
What would you think if we get this panic.
你认为是什么问题造成这个错误。
Anybody?
有人知道吗？
What memories being unmapped here, most likely.
这里取消映射的是最有可能是哪些内存？
The one that was lazily allocated not actually allocated.
那个懒分配但实际没有分配的。
Yeah, exactly the memory [] lazily allocated, but actually it hasn't been used yet, right.
是的，是懒分配的内存，但实际上还没有分配。
And so there is no physical page for that particular lazy memory.
所以，对于懒分配的内存，还没有物理页面。
And so, in this case when the pte is zero, you know there's no mapping yet,
因此，在这种情况下，当 pte 为零时，就是还没有映射，
that's not really panic, you know this is actually what we expect you know could happen right.
这并不是真的错误，这实际上是我们期望的发生的。
And in fact for that page, you don't have to do anything,
事实上，对于这一页来说，你不需要做任何事，
you can just continue to go to the next page.
你可以继续，转到下一页。
Does that make sense?
这个能理解吗？
So let's do that, now those are the echo hi,
那我们就这么做，现在执行 echo hi ，
and we've got two page faults, but hi works,
我们得到两个页面错误，但是 hi （命令）起作用了，
and so we're basically you know have sort of a very basic minimal lazy allocation scheme working.
所以，我们有了一种非常基本的懒分配方案。
Any questions about this?
关于这个，有什么问题吗？
Sorry, I didn't really follow, why you could just continue, could you explain that again.
抱歉，我没听懂，为什么你可以继续，你能再解释一遍吗？
Yeah, so the the bug indicated that we had were trying to free page that actually is not mapped.
是的，所以这个 bug 表示我们正在释放未映射的页面。
And you know how could that happen, well the only reason that could happen is
这是怎么发生的，唯一的原因是，
because sbrk moved up p->sz,
因为 sbrk 向上移动了 p->sz ，
but never used, the application never used in that memory
但是这个应用程序从未使用过这个内存，
and so it actually has no mapping yet, because it was actually not allocated.
所以它实际上还没有映射，因为它没有被分配。
Because we're lazily allocating, we're only allocating physical memory for those pages when we need it,
因为我们是懒分配，只在需要时才为这些页面分配物理内存，
if we didn't need it, then there will be no mapping
如果我们不需要它，那么就不会有映射，
and so it's totally reasonable that there actually is going to be a case
所以出现这种情况是完全合理的，
where there's no mapping for virtual address, because they're actually wasn't allocated yet.
虚拟地址还没有映射，因为他们实际上还没有被分配。
And for that case, we just have to do nothing,
这种情况下，我们什么都不用做，
you know, we can free the page, but there is no free page,
我们可以释放这一页，但是没有页面要释放，
and so the best thing is to continue and just go to the next page in the loop.
所以，最好的办法就是继续，转到循环的中的下一页。
Okay, that makes sense, thank you.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
Yeah, if we didn't do continue, but basically you know just kept going,
是的，如果我们不是继续，但是继续往前，
then we would actually create a page that would be you can do free the page,
然后我们可以创建一个页面，这样你就可以释放这个页面了，
that's why it continues there.
这就是为什么这里是继续。
Make sense.
理解了。
Another question,
我也有一个问题，
in uvmunmap, I assumed the panic was that was there was there for a reason,
在 uvmunmap 中，我认为 panic 是有原因的，
so a more correct a more reasonable implementation is to have two versions
所以，更合理的实现是使用两个版本，
and we would use the one that doesn't panic.
然后我们使用不会 panic 的那个。
Yeah, because why was the the panic,
是的，因为为什么会 panic ，
while it was basically an invariant that used to be true for unmodified xv6,
它是一个不变量，对于未修改的 xv6 来说，这是正确的，
actually unmodified xv6 should never have a case where those user memory that was not map.
实际上，未修改的 xv6 永远不应该存在用户内存未映射的情况。
And so therefore the panic goes up,
所以，出现了 panic ，
we now change the design of xv6,
我们现在修改了 xv6 的设计，
so we have to adjust and this invariant is no longer true,
所以我们必须调整，这个不变量不再是真的，
so we've got to remove the panic
所以我们必须消除 panic ，
and because that invariant is just not true, legitimately not true anymore.
因为那个不变量不再是真的，合理地，不再是真的。
I see, thanks.
我明白了，谢谢。
That makes sense?
这能理解吗？
So, so a couple comments,
所以，有几条[评论]，
this will hopefully help a lot with next lab,
希望这对下一个实验有帮助，
in fact this is one of the three components of the lab, of the next lab,
实际上，这是下一个实验的三个组成部分之一，
one of the first things you have to do
是你必须做的第一件事，
and hopefully this will save you some time,
希望这能帮你节省一些时间，
maybe make up for all the pain that you went through in the page fault lab.
或许可以降低你在页面错误实验的痛苦。
But clearly not enough right,
但显然还不够，
yeah, so like what things are,
很多东西是，
you know, we made these changes,
我们做了一些改变，
but more things are still probably broken.
但可能还有更多的东西被破坏。
One already was mentioned,
已经提到的一个是，
I actually didn't do it to check whether actually the virtual address was below p->sz
我没有检查虚拟地址是否低于 p->sz ，
which we probably should do.
这是我们应该做的。
Any other things that might be broken?
还有什么东西可能被破坏了吗？
Anybody?
有人知道吗？
Number of bytes to grow the process by sbrk is an int and not an unsigned int,
通过 sbrk 增加的进程字节数，是一个整型而不是无符号整型，
so negative numbers could be used.
所以可以使用负数。
Yes, and negative numbers can use and that means shrinking the address space,
是的，可以使用负数，这意味着缩小地址空间，
so if we shrink the address space,
所以如果我们缩小地址空间，
we also have to be a little careful.
我们也要小心一点。
So it turns out there's a whole bunch of, as usual, in an operating system and a whole bunch of different cases, right,
所以在操作系统中有很多不同的情况，
where which we're going to be looking at this particular pagetable entry
在那里，我们要查看这个页表条目，
and for all those different cases we might actually have to modify xv6 slightly.
对于所有这些不同的情况，我们可能需要修改 xv6 。
And that's exactly what basically the lab is about
这正是实验的目的所在，
is you know doing good enough job that basically you can pass usertests.
要做得足够好，你需要通过 usertests 。
Usertests will stress a whole bunch of other cases that you will need to deal with.
usertests 会有很多你需要处理的情况。
Okay?
好吧?
Any questions so far?
目前为止，有什么问题吗？
Okay, let me,
好的，让我，
in that case I want to talk about a bunch of other usages or cool things you can do
我想讲一下其他用途或你可以做的很酷的事情，
once you have page faults and pagetables are updated dynamically.
一旦你有了页面错误，页表可以动态更新。
Another one that is almost trivial, but you know commonly used
另一个几乎是微不足道的，但是经常使用的，
is what's called zero filled, zero fill on demand.
就是按需补零。
It turns out that in operating systems, you know there are many null pages.
事实上，在操作系统中，有很多空页。
And, so, for example if you look at the address space in user space,
如果你查看用户地址空间，
xv6 doesn't really is not as [advanced],
xv6 并不是很[先进]，
but if you look at the layout of a binary,
如果你看一下二进制文件的布局，
I mean [],
我的意思是，
you know there's some text, there's what's called the data segment
这有一些文本，这有数据段，
and there's typically also what something is called the BSS segment.
而且通常还有所谓的 BSS 段。
And so when the compiler produces a binary,
所以，当编译器生成二进制文件时，
you know basically fills in these three segments,
基本上填充这三个部分，
the text you know the instructions,
文本是指令，
you know the data is basically global variables, that actually have a value that is not zero, so initialized data.
数据是全局变量，它的值不是零，所以是初始化数据。
In BBS, is basically a description,
在 BBS 里，是一种描述，
that says well there's a whole bunch of variables
说明这里有很多变量，
and it's basically their sizes and they all should be zero.
它们的大小，它们应该都是零。
And the reason that they are basically not listed out,
它们没有被列出来的原因是，
you know or the memory is not right there in the files,
或者这些内存不在文件中，
because it will save a lot of
因为这会节省大量的，
for example, if you declare big matrix in C,
比如，如果你在 C 中声明一个大矩阵，
on the top of the file is a global variable
文件顶部是一个全局变量，
and it's automatically attribute zeros,
它会自动将属性设置为零，
why allocate all the space in the file,
为什么要分配文件中的所有空间，
just like no that basically you know for this particular variable in the content should be zero.
就像是，对于内容中的这个变量，应该是零。
And amazingly on exec, on a normal operating system on exec,
令人惊讶的是，在普通操作系统的 exec 上，
we'll look at these three segments,
我们来看看这三个部分，
[] usual thing that xv6 does for text and data,
像 xv6 对文本和数据做的操作，
but for BSS, it will allocate you know memory to hold the BSS and basically stick zeroes in there.
但是对 BSS ，它会分配内存来保存 BSS ，并将其置零。
So, allocated address space takes data in it
所以，分配地址空间，其中有数据，
and then we're basically look at, the equivalent of the BSS,
然后我们查看，这个相当于 BSS ，
you know all the global variables that basically zero
所有的全局变量都是零，
and maybe many many pages,
也许还有很多很多页，
and all those pages basically have to have the content zero,
所有这些页内容都是零，
so that's the virtual address space.
这就是虚拟地址空间。
And so typical trick, you know, to do is
所以，一般的技巧是，
to say like wow, I've got so many pages that need to have zero,
有很多的页面需要是零，
what I'm gonna do in physical memory,
我要在物理内存中做的是，
this is the virtual address space and the physical address memory,
这是虚拟地址空间和物理地址内存，
what I'm gonna do is you're going to allocate one zero page, and fill it with zeros,
我要做的是，你可以分配一个零页，把它填满零，
and basically map all the other pages to that one page.
然后把所有其他页面（需要是零的）都映射到这一页。
You know saving myself, you know lots you know, lots of physical memory, at least at start up.
这节省了很多物理内存，至少在开始阶段。
And of course those mappings has to be limit care, dominate care,
当然，这些映射必须是特殊对待，
we can't, you know we cannot allow write to it right,
我们不允许对它写入，
because everybody's relying on the fact that actually stays zero,
因为每个页都依赖于它保持为零，
so we just map it read only.
所以，我们把它映射为只读。
And then, at some point, when an application starts writing to one of
然后，在某个时候，当应用程序开始写入，
you know that basically started as a loader and in store, if one of the pages that actually part of the BSS,
开始加载或保存 BSS 中的页面，
so because he wants you to whatever store one or two there content there,
因为它想在那里保存内存，
we'll going to get a page fault.
我们会得到页面错误。
And so what should we do on the page fault, in this particular case.
那么，在这种情况下，我们应该如何处理页面错误呢？
Anybody?
有人知道吗？
Go ahead, anybody, I do what should we do in the page fault here.
继续，有人吗，在这个页面错误，我们应该怎么做。
I think we should make a new page and all write zeroes and rerun that instruction.
我想我们应该新建一页，都写入零，并重新运行该指令。
Yeah exactly,
是的，正确，
so let's let's assume this were my drawing, that's actually the store instruction happens to one of the top.
我们假设我画的，有一个存储指令发生在这里。
And what we really want to do basically is
我们真正想做的是，
allocate a new physical page, a page memory you know kalloc, put zeros in there,
使用 kalloc 分配一个新的物理页面，将其置零，
because you know that's what we're expecting
因为这就是我们想要的，
and then we can change the top mapping for the one for this particular,
然后我们可以把顶部映射修改为这个映射，
because this guy [], let me assume that there's this one,
因为这个页面，假设是这个，
we can change this mapping, you know to be read write,
我们可以修改这个映射为读写，
and pointed to the new page,
并指着这个新页面，
and then you basically so copy or update pte, and then restart the instruction.
然后更新 PTE ，并重启指令。
And that's it.
就是这样。
Why is this an effective
为什么这是一种有效的，
why, why do we think this is actually a good optimization.
为什么我们认为这是一个很好的优化。
Why do operating systems do it.
为什么操作系统这么做。
Anybody?
有人知道吗？
You don't need it though.
你不需要它。
Go ahead.
继续。
You don't need to use as much memory as the user requests,
你不需要使用用户要求的那么多内存，
so it's just better to build it when it when you need it.
所以更好的是在你需要的时候创造它。
Yeah, makes sense, similar to the lazy allocation,
是啊，有道理，类似于懒分配，
basically if the program say allocated huge you know array
如果程序说分配了巨大的列表，
or you know for the worst possible input,
或者对于糟糕的输入，
it's a global array, it all has to be zero,
它是一个全局数组，它全部为零，
but maybe only fraction is being used.
但可能只有一小部分被使用。
What's the second advantage.
第二个优势是什么？
Second advantage you have to do less work in exec
第二个优势是，你在 exec 中需要做的工作更少，
and so the program may start quicker and get basically better interactive performance,
所以，程序可能会启动更快，获得更好的交互性能，
because you don't really have to allocate memory,
因为你实际上不需要分配内存，
you don't really have zero memory,
你不需要将内存置零，
you only have to allocate zero one page
你只需要分配一个零页，
and the rest like just mapping the pagetables,
其他只是映射页表，
you just have to write the pte entries.
你只需写入 PTE 条目。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
But our updates or writes, so they will become slower,
但是我们的更新或写入会变慢，
because every time a page fault will occur and.
因为每次都会发生页面错误。
Yeah so you know there's absolute point,
是的，这是绝对有道理的，
so we basically postponed some of the cost later, right,
所以我们推迟了一些花费，
at the point that we do the page fault,
在我们执行页面错误时，
and you know partially relying or hoping that maybe not all the pages are being used.
依赖或希望并不是所有的页面都被使用了。
Good like for example if the pages four ninety six four thousand ninety six bytes,
比如，如果页面是 4096 字节，
you know basically we're gonna take one page fault per 4096 zeros, right.
基本上我们每 4096 个零就有一个页面错误。
And so do some [] there.
那里有一些[]。
But it's a great point,
但这是一个很好的观点，
you know certainly we've made page, we have added the cost of the page fault.
我们增加了页面错误的成本。
How much is the cost of the page fault, how should we think about that.
页面错误的成本是多少，我们应该怎么考虑？
These are comparable to store instruction more is much more expensive.
这些与存储指令相比，成本要高得多。
More expensive, right.
更高。
Yeah, why.
是的，为什么。
Store will just like need to record, it will take some time to get to the to RAM,
保存需要时间访问内存，
but the fault will have to go to the kernel.
但是，错误必须访问内核。
Yeah, so, in fact how many store instruction were there,
是的，那么，有多少个保存指令，
even in the, the trap handling code that Robert showed you last week
像 Robert 上周展示给你的 trap 处理代码，
or actually that you're doing currently in the trap lab.
或者你在 trap 实验中所做的。
Well at least like a hundred.
好吧，至少有一百个。
Yeah at least a hundred, correct, used to save store registers.
是的，至少有一百个，需要保存寄存器。
So there's quite a bit
所以有相当多的，
and so there's both the overhead of transferring from user space to kernel space as well
所以，从用户空间到内核空间的开销也很大，
as all the instructions that are being executed to save and restore state.
还有所有用来保存和恢复状态的指令。
So page fault is definitely not free,
所以，页面错误肯定不是免费的，
so the question that was asked earlier very good question.
所以，之前提出的问题是非常好的问题。
Okay.
好的。
So let's look at some more optimizations that what can do,
让我们来看一些更多能做的优化，
these ones are sort of reasonable boring, or maybe reasonable straightforward,
这些都是非常无聊的，或者非常直接的，
and we're gonna hopefully get a little bit more couple more exciting ones.
我们希望有更多更令人兴奋的（优化）。
See what is next what I wanted to do about it.
看看下一步我想做什么。
Next one, it's a very common one, in many operating systems implemented
下一个，是非常常见的，在许多操作系统中实现了，
and the fact that will also be one of the topics in the one of the labs.
实际上，这也是其中一个实验的一个主题。
So let's do the next one.
那么让我们来做下一个。
And that is copy-on-write fork, or something called COW fork.
这就是写入时复制 fork ，或者称为 COW fork 。
And you know, observation is pretty straightforward,
[观察]是非常直截了当的，
in fact we made this observation a couple times in lecture.
实际上，我们已经在讲座中做过几次[观察]。
Um, but when.
但是，当。
Let's say you know the shell, we're talking [] a second ago,
比如 shell ，我们刚才讨论的，
so shell runs and process's command
shell 运行进程命令，
and it actually does fork to create child,
它实际上执行 fork 来创建子进程，
and so the fork you know basically keep copy of shell
所以 fork 保留了 shell 的副本，
and so we got a parent and we got the child
所以我们既有父进程又有子进程，
and the child almost one of the first things it does is an exec,
而子进程做的第一件事就是 exec ，
maybe execute a couple of instructions
或许执行几条指令，
and then actually execs, for example to run echo.
然后执行 exec ，比如运行 echo  。
And as we now know, saw in last lab,
正如我们所知，在上一个实验中看到的，
you know the fork creates a complete duplicate of the shell address space,
fork 创建了 shell 地址空间的完全副本，
and then exec the first thing that basically does,
然后 exec 做的第一件事，
it throws out away and replaces it with an address space containing echo.
它会丢弃它，并将其替换为包含 echo 的地址空间。
And so it seems slightly wasteful right,
所以这看起来有点浪费，
yeah, so here let's say we have our parent virtual address space,
比如，这里我们有自己的父虚拟地址空间，
and then here we have a child.
然后，这里我们有了一个子（地址空间）。
And what we're actually doing in user physical memory,
我们在用户物理内存中实际做的是，
and in the normal case in xv6 or in unmodified xv6,
在正常的 xv6 或未修改的 xv6 中，
you know there's a bunch of like there were four pages, we saw that the shell has one two three four.
我们之前看到的 shell 有四个页面，一二三四。
And, you know when we start, when fork runs,
当运行 fork 时，
basically you do look at those four pages one two three four
查看这四个页面，一二三四，
and copy all the content you know from those pages the parent into the child.
并把父（地址空间）的所有内容复制到子（地址空间）。
And then as soon as the exec happens, basically we're going to free these pages.
然后，一旦 exec 发生，我们就会释放这些页面。
And allocate new pages actually have the content of echo in it.
并且分配新的页面，包含 echo 的内容。
So, a good organization one that actually tends to be very effective for this particular sequence
所以，对于这种情况，有一种好的组织方式是非常有效的，
is that you know if we if the parent has these four mappings, you know in its address space,
如果父进程在它的地址空间中有四个映射，
going from whatever the zero goes here, the first one goes there and whatever.
比如，零在这里，一在这里，等等。
Instead, when we create the child's address space,
当我们创建子进程的地址空间时，
instead of creating copying and allocating new physical memory,
不是复制或分配新的物理内存，
what we could do is just share the physical pages that parent actually already has allocated.
而是共享父进程已经分配的物理页面。
And so we just set the ptes with child to the same pointing to the same physical pages as in the parent.
所以，我们只是把子进程的 pte 指向父进程物理页面的相同位置。
And we're going to be a little careful again, correct,
我们要更小心一点，
because if the child wants to modify one of these pages,
因为如果子进程想要修改其中一个页面，
that updates should not be visible to the parent,
那个更新不应该对父进程可见，
because we want strong isolation between the parent and child,
因为我们希望父进程和子进程之间有很强的隔离，
so we need to be a little more careful,
所以我们需要更小心一点，
so to be a little more careful about,
所以为了更小心一点，
what we can do is just map those pages both the child and the parent read only.
我们能做的就是，将这些子页面和父页面的映射都设置为只读。
And then of course we're going to get a page fault at some point,
当然，我们也会在某一时刻得到页面错误，
because the parent is going to run where the child is going to run.
因为父进程要运行子进程运行的（位置）。
And, maybe you know the child or parent will do a store instruction
或许子进程或父进程执行保存指令，
to maybe save the data to some global variable somewhere,
可能将数据保存到某个全局变量中，
and at that point you know, that that will cause a page fault,
在这时，会导致页面错误，
because you were writing to a page that is mapped read only,
因为你正在写入的页面，映射为只读，
we get a page fault
我们得到一个页面错误，
and so what do we need to do.
那么我们需要做什么。
Well, we need to make a copy of the page,
我们需要把那个页面复制一份，
so let's assume that's the child that actually does the store instruction,
我们假设子进程执行存储指令，
so we allocate a new page,
所以我们分配一个新的页面，
we copy the content of of the page that were faulted on into this new page,
我们复制出现错误的页面内容到新页面，
we map that page into the child,
我们把那一页映射到子进程中，
and this guy we can map read write,
而这个我们可以映射为读写，
because now private page only visible in the child's address space,
因为私有页面仅在子进程的地址空间中可见，
in fact the page that actually will be fault on,
实际上，出错的页面，
we can also now map page read write into the parent.
我们现在也可以将父进程页面（标记为）读写。
And so we copy the page, map it and restart instruction.
所以，我们复制页面，映射它，然后重启指令。
And when restarting starting really means you know doing userret
重启意思是，执行 userret ，
the same way that return to user space, in the last week's lecture.
与上周的讲座中返回用户空间的方法相同。
Does this make sense, any questions about this one.
这能理解吗，关于这个，有什么问题吗。
I'm sorry, when you say we mapped the parents virtual address to we also read write,
抱歉，当你说我们把父进程的虚拟地址映射为读写，
how do we find it out, is the same as the child's?
我们如何找到它，跟子进程的一样吗？
Yeah because the address space of the child is a duplicate of the parents address space right,
是的，因为子进程的地址空间是父进程地址空间的副本，
so if we fault to a particular virtual address,
所以，如果我们在一个虚拟地址出现错误，
seems the address spaces are equal,
地址空间是相等的，
you know the same virtual address both the parents address space and in the child's address space.
同一个虚拟地址，同时在父进程的地址空间和子进程的地址空间。
Makes sense, thank you.
理解了，谢谢。
Another question?
另一个问题？
Yeah.
嗯。
For, let's say, like some parent [] process, maybe like the first one that launches,
比如，某个没有父进程的进程，或许第一个启动的，
does it use its pages, god, does it set just read permissions
它是否使用它的页面设置位读权限，
or does it start off with read write, when it forks it modifies.
或者以读写开始，当它 fork 时。
OK, OK, it's up to you,
好的，这是由你决定的，
if I knew this is also one lab,
这也是一个实验，
you can implement copy-on-write after the lazy lab,
你可以在 lazy 实验后实现写入时复制，
you have some freedom
你有一些自由，
and an easy thing to do is just also map read only,
容易做的是映射为只读，
you will get a page fault,
你会得到页面错误，
and then you do whatever you normally also would do in the copy-on-write.
然后，你可以执行在写入时复制时也会执行的操作。
So you can use the same mechanism, in both cases.
所以，在这两种情况下，你可以使用相同的机制。
There's no reason to actually specialize for some separate for the first process.
没有理由对第一个进程专门处理。
Okay thanks.
好的，谢谢。
So, I also have a question,
我也有一个问题，
given that we like kind of copy whole tables, sorry, whole pages around pretty often,
考虑到我们经常复制整个页面，
does any, like memory hardware implement like a specific instruction,
存储器硬件有没有实现一个特殊指令，
because basically memory hardware will usually just have like some data lines
因为内存硬件通常只有一些行，
to say read me or stored just memory,
读取或保存内存，
but we have like [] copy page a to page b.
但是我们有把 a 页复制到 b 页。
Yeah, x86 example has hardware instructions for copying range of memory.
是的， x86 有复制内存范围的硬件指令。
You know RISC-V doesn't.
RISC-V 没有。
Um, yeah, but of course you know in, in a very high performance implementation,
是的，当然在非常高性能实现中，
all the reads writes will be pipelined,
所有读取写入会使用流水线，
in hopefully run at the speed of the memory bandwidth.
希望以内存带宽的速度运行。
Note that actually, in principle, we might be lucky and we're saving, correct, on loads and stores or copies,
注意，原则上，我们会幸运地在加载和存储或复制时[节省]，
because in this particular picture, I made only one copy
因为在这张图片里，我只复印了一份，
and in the unmodified case, we would have copied all four pages.
而在未修改的情况下，我们会复制全部四页。
And so, hopefully this is strictly better, both in terms of memory consumption and in terms of performance,
所以，无论是在存储器消耗方面还是在性能方面，这是更好的，
you know fork will just be faster.
fork 会更快。
I have a quick question,
我有一个问题，
when when the page fault occurs
当页面错误发生时，
and we see that it was essentially like we were trying to write to a read only address,
我们看到本质上是我们试图写入只读地址，
how does the kernel tell, like this is a situation where it's copy-on-write fork
内核是如何知道这是一种写入时复制 fork 的情况，
versus just a situation where the memory it was trying to write was was marked as read only for some legitimate reason
而不是试图写入因为某些合法原因标记位只读的内存，
other than copy-on-write fork
而不是写入时复制 fork ，
is just kind of an invariance that if a its user memory,
在内存中是一种不变量，
then it will be mapped read write, unless it was a result of copy-on-write fork.
然后它被映射为读写，除非它是写入时复制 fork 的结果。
Yeah yeah, so it is an invariant that needs to be maintained in the kernel
是的，所以它是一个需要在内核中维护的不变量，
and the kernel must recognize in some way that this is a copy-on-write page, if you will.
内核必须以某种方式识别这是写入时复制页面，
And so I'm very glad you asked the question,
我很高兴你问了这个问题，
because it turns out you know the RISC-V hardware, almost all pagetable hardware actually has support for this.
因为 RISC-V 硬件，几乎所有的可分页硬件都支持这一点。
And we didn't mention it earlier,
我们之前没有提过，
but here's are usual you know, whatever two level, or multilevel pagetable use pte,
我们使用的两级或多级的页表都使用 pte ，
and you're looking at pte, you know I talked about the bits you know one zero through seven,
你看到的 pte ，我讲过 0 到 7 的标志位，
but not about these two bits, RSW.
但没讲过这两个位， RSW 。
And, they are reserved for supervisor software.
它们是为管理软件保留的。
So the supervisor software, this is the kernel, you can use these bits at its own free will.
所以管理软件，内核可以随意使用这些位。
And so one thing one could do is
所以可以做的一件事是
like say decide that being a basically means this is a copy-on-write page or copy-on-write fault.
决定是一个写入时复制页面还是写入时复制错误。
And so when the kernel programs these page tables for copy-on-write,
所以当内核把这些页表用于写入时复制，
you can just put on the ptes, you know for these particular pages, the bits,
你可以直接设置这些页面的 pte 的位，
you know set to be a copy-on-write,
设置为写入时复制，
so that when the page fault happens
在发生页面错误时，
and we see that the copy-on-write bit set,
我们看到设置了写入时复制位，
then we just go off into this,
那我们到这里（之前的情况），
and otherwise we do something else, for example, maybe the lazy allocation.
否则我们就做些别的事，比如，可能是懒分配。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Yep, thank you.
好的，谢谢你。
And in fact in in the lab, one of the things you will be doing is
实际上，在实验中，你要做的一件事是，
probably use that bit you know set a copy-on-write in the pte.
使用这个位在 pte 中设置写入时复制。
There's one more [] that will show up in the copy-on-write lab
还有一个[]将在写入时复制实验中显示出来，
is that there's some currently in xv6, basically a physical page more or less only belongs to one process,
目前在 xv6 中，一个物理页面或多或少只属于一个进程，
with the exception of the trampoline page, which that trampoline were never free,
除了 trampoline 页面，它从来不会被释放，
so that's not really going to a particular big issue.
所以这不是一个特别大的问题。
But for these pages you now we have multiple processes or multiple address spaces pointing to the same physical address,
但是，对于那些有多个进程或者多个地址指向相同物理地址的页面，
and so, for example if the parent exits right away,
比如，如果父进程立即退出，
we're gonna live with care and be careful right,
我们就要小心，
because can we free that page immediately, if the parent exits.
因为如果父进程退出，我们能立即释放那一页吗。
Maybe not, because there may be multiple children processes.
可能不能，因为可能有多个子进程。
Yeah, there might be child using that page
是啊，可能有子进程在用那个页面，
and so we've kernel would free that page, then, you know we're gonna be in trouble,
内核将释放该页面，那么我们会有麻烦，
because basically the if you look at kfree,
因为如果你看一下 kfree ，
kfree actually writes all kinds once on a free page
一旦释放页面， kfree 会写入所有[类型]，
and so then the child runs with that page
然后子进程使用那一页运行，
and all kinds of bizarre things are gonna happen.
各种奇怪的事情就会发生。
So what should you be now for free.
那么，现在释放应该怎么做呢？
Free, if you don't have children, I guess.
我想是在没有子进程的情况下释放。
Yeah, we may be better way of sort of a more general version of that statement
是的，我们用更一般的方式来解释这一说法，
is to say well what we really need to do is we need a ref count every physical page.
就是我们需要做的是，每个物理页面有一个 ref 计数。
And when we free the page, we decrease the ref down by one
当我们释放页面时，我们将引用减少 1 ，
and if the ref count reaches zero, then actually we can free the page.
如果引用计数达到零，那么我们就可以释放页面了。
And so you will have to introduce some additional data structure or meta information in the copy-on-write,
所以，你必须在写入时复制中引入一些额外的数据结构或元信息，
[] actually do that ref counting.
用来做引用计数。
Where can we store this,
我们把这个存放在哪里，
because this if we ever have the ref count every single page, that can be a lot.
因为如果每一页都有引用计数，这会是很多。
Yeah well for every physical page of memory, we will have to do a ref count.
是的，对于内存的每一个物理页面，我们必须有引用计数。
Yeah, you can get away with a little bit less,
是的，你可以少一点，
but then we're in for simplification in lab,
但在实验里进行简化，
we're just for everyone for every 4096 bytes,
对于每 4096 字节，
we need to contain a reference count.
我们需要包含一个引用计数。
Can we write that down in those other two free bits and say that, no more than four.
我们能不能把它写在另外两个空闲位上，然后说，不超过 4 。
Good yeah, not unreasonable,
很好，不是不合理，
but you know if you're fork it multiple times,
但是如果你把它 fork 多次，
that be too bad, right,
那就太糟糕了，
after three times or four times, you can't do can't do the optimization anymore.
三四次之后，你就不能再做优化了。
Yeah there's some freedom here.
是的，这里有一些自由。
Also, do you really need to use that bit to specify if it's a copy-on-write,
还有，你真的需要用那个位来指定它是不是写入时复制，
because the kernel could also maintain some information about the processes that.
因为内核也可以维护有关进程的一些信息。
Yeah yeah yeah, you could you could do anything,
是的，你可以做任何事，
some other matter information along with the process address space
一些其他事项信息连同进程地址空间，
to say basically well virtual addresses between this and that are text addresses,
比如在这个和那个之间的虚拟地址是文本地址，
so we have a page fault there and it must be copy-on-write or something.
所以，我们在那里有一个页面错误，它一定是写入时复制或其他什么。
In fact one of the later labs,
实际上，后来的一个实验里，
you know you'll certainly extend the meta information that xv6 maintains, exactly for that reason.
你会扩展 xv6 维护的元信息，正是这个原因。
There's a bit of freedom here and when you start implementing these labs.
这里有一些自由，当你开始实现这些实验时。
Any further questions about this?
关于这个，还有什么问题吗？
Okay, let's go to the next one, there's something called demand paging,
好的，让我们进入下一个，叫做按需调页，
another very popular one in most operating systems implemented.
是另一个在大多数操作系统中非常流行的。
And so the you know it just goes back basically to exec.
所以，它是回到了 exec 。
So currently in unmodified xv6,
目前在未修改的 xv6 中，
you know xv6 loads the text segment, and the data segment profile
xv6 加载文本段，和数据段，
and maps in eagerly in basically into the pagetable.
并急切地映射到页表中。
And basically the same observation that we made for lazy and zero filled,
和我们对懒分配和置零观察到的一样，
is that well what we could do is like why do it eagerly,
我们可以做的是，为什么要急切地去做，
why not just wait a little while, until to see if actually the application really needs,
为什么不等一会儿，直到看到应用程序是否真的需要，
you know those particular set of instructions, you know the binary might be very big.
那些特别的指令，二进制文件可能会很大。
In instead of actually loading it all in you know from disk,
不是真的从磁盘中全部加载进去，
it tends to be expensive operation,
它往往是昂贵的操作，
maybe the data segment is much bigger than really needs than the typical use case requires,
可能数据段比实际需要的要大得多，
we don't really have to do that.
我们没必要这么做。
And so instead of, on exec, instead of actually we allocate the virtual address space,
所以，在 exec 中，不是真正分配虚拟地址空间，
you know allocate the address space for the text and the data that's in the file,
为文件里的文本和数据分配地址空间，
but in the ptes were not mapped all,
但在 pte 中并没有全部映射，
we're just gonna keep you know pte for one of these pages,
我们只会保留其中一页，
we just cannot set valid bit, so valid bit to zero.
我们不能设置有效位，因此有效位为零。
And of course you know, when we're gonna get our first page fault,
当然，在我们得到第一个页面错误时，
if we do this in exec and let's say we modify xv6 to do this.
如果我们在 exec 中这样做，比如修改 xv6 来做这个。
When will our first page fault happen,
当第一个页面错误发生时，
what's the first instruction that is being run for user address or user program.
为用户地址或用户程序运行的第一条指令是什么。或用户程序。
Where does the user program start.
用户程序从哪里开始。
Is it loading the initial code, in uvminit.
是不是在 uvminit 中的加载初始代码。
Yeah okay, we're just [],
是的，好的，我们只是[]，
modifying exec and not called the uvminit, where.
修改的 exec 没有调用 uvminit ，其中。
So mostly when we actually if you remember from for [] or something like that,
所以大多数情况下，如果你还记得[]或类似的东西，
you know the place where an application starts exactly address zero,
应用程序是从地址零开始的，
pictures a little bit is leading here,
图片中的这里，
but here's text, here zero it goes up to some number
但是这是文本，这里是零，它上升到某个数字，
and basically the first instruction whatever sits here,
第一条指令在这里，
that's the first instruction that we're gonna actually,
这是我们实际上的第一个指令，
that address, that's the first instruction, we're going to get a page fault, right.
那个地址，是第一条指令，我们会得到页面错误。
Because we have not loaded it.
因为我们还没有加载它。
So what do you want the page fault.
那么你想要什么页面错误。
Well we're going to do in the page fault,
好的，我们将在页面错误中做的是，
it's basically will note that this is one of these on demand pages,
注意到这是其中一个按需页面，
we have to remember somewhere earlier,
我们要事先在某个地方记住，
that you know this corresponds to some, that this corresponds to some file.
这对应于一些文件。这对应于某个文件。
Imagine what we're gonna do in the page fault handler is read, you know that block page from file into memory,
假设我们在页面错误处理代码中要做的是把页面从文件读到内存中，
map the memory into the pagetable,
将内存映射到页表中，
then restart the instruction,
然后重启指令，
and, then we're off for running right.
然后，我们就可以继续运行了。
And so we're gonna go in the worst case,
所以在最坏的情况下，
if the user program uses all of its text, uses all of this data,
如果用户程序使用所有文本，使用所有数据，
then we're going to get a page fault for every page, you know in the, in the program.
那么我们会在程序的每一个页面都有一个页面错误。
But you know we get lucky in the program,
但是，如果我们在这个程序中很幸运，
it doesn't use all of its data segment
它不会使用所有数据段，
or doesn't use all of its text segment,
或者不会使用所有文本段，
then we might save some memory
那么我们可能会节省一些内存，
and we certainly make exec you know perform, you know, much quicker
我们当然会让 exec 表现得更快，
and it'll be a little bit more interactive,
它会更具互动性，
assumes the program starts boom it's running,
假设程序开始运行，
well we actually have to do any work exactly.
我们必须准确地做任何工作。
Does that makes this observation makes sense?
这个能理解吗？
Okay so there's a slight extension to demand paging, so this is the second part of the demand paging.
好的，按需调页有一个扩展，这是按需调页的第二部分。
Right, there's more.
是的，这里还有更多。
Part two demand paging,
按需调页的第二部分，
in principle, there's a little bit of problem here,
原则上，这里有一点小问题，
that we haven't really discussed,
我们还没有真正讨论过，
it might be the case,
可能是这样的，
may be the file that we're actually reading
可能就是我们真正在读的文件，
or the text and data segments are even bigger than what actually is in physical memory,
或者文本和数据段甚至比物理内存更大，
or if multiple applications started with demand paging,
或者多个应用程序以按需调页开始，
maybe there's some of their binarys, it's basically bigger than there actually is a physical memory.
也许有一些它们的二进制文件，比物理内存要大。
And so, the typical thing you know what, if you go down this demand paging,
所以，如果你深入按需调页，
[] is to actually if you run out of memory,
如果你的内存耗尽，
so if kalloc returns zero, it's out of memory.
如果 kalloc 返回零，就是内存不足。
So, for example, you know your demand page,
比如，你的按需页面，
you get a page fault at some page, that needs to be a paged in from a file system,
你在需要从文件系统调入的页面出现页面错误，
but you don't have any more free pages, you need to do something.
但是你没有更多的空闲页面，你需要做些什么。
And so the typical this comes back to earlier question,
所以又回到了前面的问题，
for example the same is to for lazy or
比如，跟懒分配类似，
you know what to do if you run out of memory.
如果你的内存用完了，该怎么做。
So if you run out of memory,
所以如果内存用完了，
one option that you really clearly have is to evict a page.
一个很明显的选择就是逐出一个页面。
You can for example instead of you know you can for example and pick the page and write to the file back.
比如，你可以选择一个页面，写会到文件中。然后选择页面并写回文件。
So for example it's a data page that got modified,
比如，一个修改过的数据页面，
so you can write it back to the file system.
你就可以把它写回文件系统。
And then once you pick the page
一旦你选择了这一页，
and then you have a new free page
然后你就有了一个新的空闲页面，
and you can put the use that you use the new just free page,
你可以使用这个新的空闲页面，
to satisfy you know the fault that you had
来解决你遇到的错误，
and then basically restarting instruction again.
然后再次重启指令。
Again, restarting instruction is a little more complicated,
再说一次，重启指令有点复杂，
because the whole machinery to basically do userret
因为整个机制是调用 userret ，
and started and transfer back to user space, etc.
开始并转移回用户空间，等等。
And so this is a typical operating system will do this
一个典型的操作系统将执行此操作，
and of course the key question is like what page to evict.
当然，关键问题是要驱逐哪一页。
Which one to choose?
该选哪一个？
So what are some candidates
那么什么是候选者，
you know what do, what would be a reasonable policy for choosing a page to evict.
有什么合理的方法来选择一个页面来驱逐。
Least recently used.
最近最少使用。
Yeah, so this is the most commonly used strategy, least recently used, or LRU.
是的，所以这是最常用的策略，最近最少使用，或者 LRU 。
And, that was gonna page was typically is thrown out,
那是典型的被扔掉的页面，
there's a couple sort of twist typically [] some small optimizations that do,
通常有一些可以做的小优化，
if you have to pick the page
如果你必须选择一页，
and you have to choice between dirty page and non-dirty page,
你必须在脏页和非脏页之间做出选择，
so dirty pages page where there was a store to
所以，脏页是有保存（东西）的，
and non-dirty pages or pages basically has been read, but not written to,
而非脏页只有读取，没有被写入，
which one would you prefer evict first.
你选择哪一个先驱逐出去。
Dirty one, because you would have to write the dirty one at some point anyway.
脏页，因为不管怎样，你总要写脏的那个。
Yeah.
嗯。
So sorry, say again actually just double-check there.
抱歉，请再说一遍，确认一下。
I said dirty, because dirty pages would need to be written into memory at some point.
我说的是脏页，因为脏页在某一时刻需要写入内存。
Yeah that's true, then maybe now you have to write it twice,
是的，那是真的，也许现在你得写两遍，
you know once you write it may be modified later again.
一旦你写了，以后可能会再次修改。
And so actually typically.
所以实际上。
OK OK's I see.
好的，我明白了。
Exactly the opposite, they choose a page that actually has not been written or it's not dirty,
恰恰相反，选择没有写入的页或者非脏页，
because you don't have to do anything,
因为你不需要做任何事，
you can just reuse it,
你可以重新使用它，
you can just take mark if it is present in in pagetable one,
如果它在[页表一]中，你可以标记它，
you mark there is non valid and then you're done.
你标记它是无效的，就可以了。
And then you can reuse that page in another pagetable.
然后，你可以在另一个页表中重用该页面。
And so the preference intensity is a take pages that have been not non-dirty ones first.
所以偏好是首先选择非脏页。
Can I just ask for a clarification on the dirty pages.
我能不能问一下确认那些脏页。
Yeah.
嗯。
So, I I know, like in a cache,
所以，我知道，就像在缓存里，
when we have memory and then we say okay a line is dirty,
在内存中，我们说一行是脏的，
because it hasn't been written to memory,
因为它还没有被写入内存，
but what about a page in memory like what does it correspond to like, how is it dirty,
但是内存中的一页是什么样子的呢，它脏在哪里，
where does it have to be written back to,
它要写回哪里，
it just exists in memory right,
它只是存在于内存中，
isn't that the whole whole thing like it doesn't exist anywhere else really,
是不是它不存在于其他地方，
so when can it be dirty.
那么它是如何变脏的。
Yeah okay, so for example if the demand page file page,
好的，比如，如果按需页面是文件页面，
actually we'll talk about in a second,
实际上，我们稍后会谈到，
like in the next, maybe a little bit too much,
在下一个，可能有点太多了，
but if you memory map files,
但是内存映射文件，
where you map a file into memory,
你把文件映射到内存，
and then do store to it, then you would dirty that page.
然后把对它保存，那么你就会弄脏那一页。
Okay so that only applies
好的，所以这只适用于
when like a page actually response not just to some memory, but also to a file or something else.
一个页面不仅对应内存，还对应文件或其他东西。而且还可以存储到文件或其他文件中。
Okay, okay, that makes sense.
好的，理解了。
Yeah.
嗯。
Okay, so just to, you know just to make one more two more points related to this,
好的，所以我想再多说两点与此相关的观点，
if you look at this pte again,
如果你再看这个 pte ，
so we saw this RSW bit,
所以我们看这个 RSW 位，
you'll notice there actually is a bit seven, that is the dirty bit.
你会注意到第七位，就是脏页位。
So when the paging hardware where the hardware ever writes you know to page
所以当硬件曾经写入页面，
then [watch] this set dirty bits,
就会设置这个脏页位，
so the operating system later can see,
这样操作系统稍后就可以看到，
, oh, this actually page can easily see this page that's actually written to.
可以很容易地看到这个页面有写入。
And similarly there is a A bit, that stands for access,
同样的，还有一个 A 位，表示访问，
and so whenever pages either written or written either read or written the access bit will be set.
所以每当页面读取或写入，访问位会被设置。
And, and why is it useful to know?
为什么知道这一点是有用的？
In one way, could that help the kernel?
这可以以哪种方式帮助内核？
Well, the ones that haven't been accessed, you can, you can evict right.
嗯，那些还没被访问过的，你可以驱逐。
Yeah, what are you saying that if you want to implement these recently used,
是的，你的意思是如果你想实施最近用过的，
if, if you find a page that basically hasn't been accessed in some period of time,
如果你发现一个页面在一段时间内没有被访问过，
you know it actually hasn't been recently used,
你知道它最近没有被使用过，
so it actually is a candidate for eviction,
所以它是一个驱逐候选者，
while the pages that have the access bit set are not really candidates for eviction.
而设置了访问位的页面，不是驱逐候选者。
So, A bit typically used where actually is typically used to implement this LRU strategy.
所以， A 位通常用来实现这个 LRU 策略。
Okay, but would you have to reset the access bits to not access every once in a while.
好的，但是你需要每隔一段时间重置访问位为未访问。
Exactly, that's exactly what the typical operation system will do.
没错，这是操作系统会做的事情。
And if they [] even maybe for all memory,
可能所有内存，
they [sweep] for memory [],
从内存中[清除]，
famous algorithm, which is called the clock algorithm that is one way of doing it.
著名的算法，称为时钟算法，就是这样做的一种方式。
[] why would you need to set it, why would you to reset it.
为什么要设置它，为什么要重置。
Well, if you want to know when our pages recently used,
如果你想知道我们的页面最近是什么时候使用的，
you need and you make a periodic decision,
你需要做一个定期的决定，
then say maybe every hundred milliseconds or whatever every seconds,
然后比如每一百毫秒，或者其他时间，
you clear the access bit,
你清除访问位，
yeah it gets access in the next hundred milliseconds,
它在接下来的 100 毫秒内访问，
you know it was used in the last hundred milliseconds.
你知道它在过去的 100 毫秒内使用的。
And the pages that don't have the access bit set were not used in last in the milliseconds.
那些没有设置访问位的页面，在最近的毫秒内没有使用过。
And so then you can keep counters with how intentionally they used
这样你就可以记录他们如何使用，
and what is and for really especially the [steppingstone] to [sophisticate] our implementation.
特别是帮助我们实现。
Okay.
好的。
I want to talk about one more used to,
我想再谈一件事，
the last one actually you also will be implementing in one of the labs.
最后一个，你也在一个实验中实现。
And that is a memory mapped files.
这就是内存映射文件。
The idea is that you know we're we have our address space,
想法是，我们有地址空间，
what we really want to do is basically be able to load the whole file or parts of the file into the address space,
我们想做的是加载将整个文件或部分文件到地址空间中，
so that we can just manipulate the content of the file using load store instructions,
这样我们就可以使用加载存储指令来操作文件的内容，
instead of read else you can write.
你可以读或写。
And to be able to support that,
为了能够支持这一点，
you know a typical operating system where most modern operating systems called provide a system call mmap,
在大多数现代操作系统中，提供一个系统调用 mmap ，
and basically mmap takes a virtual address or pick some virtual address length, protection, flags,
mmap 使用虚拟地址，虚拟地址长度，[保护]，标志位，
we're going to talk about
我们要讨论的，
and then file descriptor of an open file and an offset.
然后是打开文件的文件描述符和偏移量。
Maybe [with] this's like you should
也许你应该，
map you know this file descriptor to this addressing a virtual address,
映射这个文件描述符到这个虚拟地址，如果这是寻址虚拟地址，
you know file descriptor starting from offset in the file f,
文件描述符从文件 f 中的偏移量开始，
you know map that in at the address at the virtual address va.
把它映射到虚拟地址 va 的地址。
And do that we have some protection read, write etc.
做这个，我们有一些[保护]，读，写等。
So let's say is read write,
我们假设是读写，
then you know the kernel when and so, the way it currently implements mmap is,
那么内核实现 mmap 的方法是，它目前实现mmap的方式，
it does eagerly, which is like most systems does do it eagerly,
它急切地做，大多数系统都急切的做，
basically copy, read all the bytes starting from offset,
复制，读取从偏移量开始的所有字节，
[] bytes starting from offset into memory,
加载从偏移量开始的字节到内存中，
sets up the ptes to point to the physical memory for blocks are located
设置 pte 指向物理内存的位置，
and basically from then on the application use [], use load and store instructions to actually modify the file
从那时起，应用程序使用加载保存指令修改文件，
and the maybe when they were all done,
当所有都完成后，
there's typically a corresponding unmap call,
会有一个对应的 unmap 调用，
that, and at length, then allows the application to say, OK I'm done with this particular file
和 len ，然后允许应用程序，我已经完成使用这个文件，
and at the point of unmap and we need to write back the dirty blocks.
在 unmap 的时候，需要把脏页写会。
And we can easily figure out which blocks are dirty,
我们可以很容易地找出哪些块是脏的，
because they have D bit set into pte.
因为它们在 PTE 中设置了 D 位。
Now, of course in any memory or sophisticated memory implementation,
现在，在任何内存或复杂的内存实现中，
this is all done [lately],
这些都是最近才做的，
you know you just don't map the file immediately,
你不是立即映射文件，
you just keep a record somewhere on the [],
你只要在某个地方保存一份记录，
saying like well you know this PTE really belongs to this particular file descriptor,
比如，这个 pte 属于这个特定的文件描述符，
so there's some information maintained on the side
所有，在旁边有一些控制信息，
which is typically called in a structure called the vma or the virtual memory area.
通常在一个结构中 vma ，或虚拟内存区。
For example, for this file f would be one vma
比如，对于此文件 f 有一个 vma ，
and in a vma we record the file descriptor the offset etc,
在 vma 中我们记录文件描述符、偏移量等，
where the actual content that then we should live
我们应该使用的内容在哪里，
and so when we get a page fault for a particular address that's in this vma,
当我们得到在 vma 中地址的页面错误时，
then we can go off and the kernel can read it from disk and bring it into memory.
然后我们可以离开，内核从磁盘读取它，加载到内存中。
And in response to an earlier question
回答早先的一个问题，
is one of the reasons that this dirty bit is important,
这个脏页位很重要的原因之一是，
because as mmap, you have to write back the dirty blocks.
因为 mmap 必须写回脏块。
Does this make sense?
这个能理解吗？
I have a question.
我有一个问题。
Maybe this is a more general issue,
也许这是一个普遍的问题，
but could it ever be an issue of say multiple process [] are memory mapping the same file on secondary storage
比如说多个进程[]是否在内存映射辅助内存相同的文件，
and then like [synchronization] is.
然后同步。
Good question, so what is the semantics in Unix in general
好问题，那么， Unix 中的语义是什么，
like what happens if multiple processes read or write to the same file using read or write system calls.
比如，如果多个进程使用读取或写入系统调用读取或写入同一文件，会发生什么情况。
Did you needs guarantee anything.
你需要保证什么吗。
It's undefined.
这是不确定的。
Yeah yeah there's like no the reason write will show up in some order
是的，写会以某种顺序出现，
or the writes will show up in some order,
或者写入将以某种顺序出现，
so if two process you write to the same block of the file,
如果两个进程写入文件中的同一块，
you know either the first process writes go or the second process writes go, one of two.
可能是第一次写的，或第二次写的，其中之一。
And so here's basically the same thing,
所以这里也是一样的东西，
we don't really have to guarantee anything.
我们不需要保证什么。
If you want to do a more sophisticated Unix operating system support file locking,
如果你想做一个更复杂的 Unix 操作系统支持文件锁，
where you can lock files and then you can properly synchronize,
在那里你可以锁定文件，然后你就可以正确地同步，
by default, there's no synchronization, or no synchronization at this level.
默认情况下，这里没有同步，或者在这一级没有同步。或者在此级别没有同步。
That makes sense?
能理解吗？
I'm sorry, what is length and what is flags.
抱歉，长度是什么，标志位是什么。
Of [like] length is the length of the you know the area you want to map the file number of bytes.
长度是你要映射的文件以字节为单位的长度。
Flags read write X flags, you know you'll see that when you do a map,
标志读写 X ，标志当你映射是会看到，
I think this has to do with whether the area is mapped private or shared.
我认为这与映射的区域是私有的还是共享的有关。
If it's mapped shared and then it can be shared among multiple processes.
如果它被映射为共享，那么它可以在多个进程之间共享。
Any further questions about this?
关于这个，还有什么问题吗？
If some other process modifies the file in this,
如果某个其他进程修改了这个文件，
that means that this will not be reflected here, right.
也就是说这个不会在这里体现出来，是吗。
That's correct, unless I think if mapped shared, then you're supposed to reflect those changes.
没错，除非映射位共享的，那么你就应该体现这些变化。
Right, but then they would be using the same file descriptor.
好的，但之后它们将使用相同的文件描述符。
I'm hazy on the exact semantics of mmap,
我对 mmap 的确切语义不清楚，
when things are shared and what exactly happens there.
当文件被分享的时候，那里会发生什么。
Okay I guess so I guess in like the idiomatic case,
好的，我想，就像习语中的情况一样，
and shared they would have to reflect it,
它们分享了，必须反映出来，
but if a process just like actually open the same file name completely set separately I think,
但是如果一个进程上打开完全相同的文件名，我想设置为分开的，
it could be a [un synced], even if it's shared.
它可以是不同步的，即使它是共享的。
Okay, so, so this is after the file system lab, you actually do memory map files.
好的，在文件系统实验之后，你会做内存映射文件。
And that will be our last virtual memory sort of lab,
这是我们最后一次虚拟内存实验，
unless you decide at the end to do more virtual memory features or exercises or whatever you wanna do,
除非你最后决定做更多虚拟内存功能或练习或者做任何你想做的事，
you know the main job is to conclude this lecture.
用主要工作来结束这节课。
The, sort of summary.
这是总结。
You know, we've lived in the past, in terms of great detail exactly how pagetables work.
我们了解了页表工作的很多细节。
We've done a couple labs, one lab of the pagetables,
我们做了几个实验，一个是页面的实验，
we've looked a lot like how traps work, and you know page fault,
我们看了 trap 和页面错误如何工作。
and it turns out if you combine the two,
如果你把这两者结合起来，
now you're gonna implement very powerful and elegant virtual memory features.
现在你将实现非常强大和优雅的虚拟内存功能。
And you know went through a whole list of them,
我列了一张清单，
mostly focusing on the ones, that actually going to be implementing future lab,
主要集中在那些将要实现的未来实验上，
but you know this is only a subset,
但是这只是一个子集，
for example of the ones that you know some operating systems implement the typical operating system to implement all the ones that actually discussed today.
比如，一些操作系统实现了今天讨论的所有这些。
If you look at Linux and as all of them.
如果你看 Linux ，所有这些都（实现了）。
And many more interesting other tricks,
还有更多有趣的技巧，
but this hopefully gives you good sense, you know sort out the power of virtual memory,
但希望这能让你更好地感受虚拟内存的力量，
once you dynamically can change the pagetables in the page fault handler.
一旦你可以在页面错误处理程序中动态修改页表。
I think there's exactly at 25,
我想正好是在 25 ，
so maybe that's a good point to stop,
所以也许是结束的时间了，
but if you have any questions, feel free to ask them.
但是如果你有任何问题，可以随意提问。
If not, you know we should, good luck finishing the trap lab.
如果没有，祝你顺利完成 trap 实验。
I hope it's not as painful as the year,
我希望不会像往年那么痛苦，
we're not as hard as the pagetable lab.
不像页面实验那么难。
Sorry I had another question,
抱歉，我有另一个问题，
when you map in the previous slide,
当你在上一张幻灯片中映射时，
when you map the whole file or when you put it into memory,
当你映射整个文件或将其放入内存时，
and it turns out to be longer than length, then, what happens.
如果发现它比长度还长，然后，会发生什么。
Sorry if the file doesn't fit in the virtual address space?
抱歉，如果文件不能放入虚拟地址空间？
Oh I guess it was like length is how much of the file, we want.
哦，我猜长度就是我们想要的文件大小。
Yes, so length, just like we want to map like ten bytes out of the file descriptor starting at offset off.
是的，长度，就像我们希望从偏移量 off 开始映射文件描述符的 10 个字节。
Oh, okay, okay, so if the file is longer than,
哦，好的，如果文件长于（length），
we're not gonna put all of it into memory.
我们不会把这它整个放入内存中。
Okay I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
I got a question, I've got a question on the evicting pages.
我有个问题，我在驱逐页面上有个问题。
So basically we talked about it after the demand paging part two,
我们在按需调页第二部分讨论了这个问题，
but is that a general procedure,
但是这是一个一般的程序吗，
we would use in any of these techniques,
我们会在这些技术中使用任何一种，
if we discover that we're out of physical boundary.
如果我们发现我们已经超越了物理边界。
Yeah that's just the common majorly mechanism,
是的，这只是常见的主要机制，
like, so even in lazy allocation,
即使在懒分配中，
we run at the point where there's no memory available anymore to allocate to the page
我们在没有可供分配给页面的内存时运行，
and you know we support demand paging
我们支持按需调页，
or whatever we evict you know some page you typically using LRU.
或者我们驱逐的任何东西，通常使用 LRU 。
Okay.
好的。
One way to think about is that in steady state,
一种考虑的方式是，在稳定状态下，
the operating system basically runs with all memory in use at any time.
操作系统基本上在任何时候都在使用所有内存的情况下运行。
And want to use all memory
希望使用所有内存，
and so when we start something new,
所以当我们开始一些新的事情时，
you know we have to make some room
我们得腾出一些地方，
and LRU is basically a way to do it.
而 LRU 就是这样做的一种方式。
Okay, makes sense, thank you.
好的，理解了，谢谢。